<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sundry reasons inducing Major Robert Huntington to lay down his commission. Humbly presented to the Honourable Houses of Parliament.</title>
            <author>Huntington, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86915</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864470</idno>
  <idno type="VID">116699</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240905409</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E458_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205025</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864470</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99864470e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86915)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116699)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 73:E458[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sundry reasons inducing Major Robert Huntington to lay down his commission. Humbly presented to the Honourable Houses of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Huntington, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeer. 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Aug. 2. 1648. Robert Huntington.</note>
                  <note>With an appended note dated 12 Aug. referring to a surreptitious edition published the previous day with aspersions on Huntington's character appended. Variant: an earlier printing, lacking the note; title has misprint "Huntingdon".</note>
                  <note>This edition has a double rule border and the fifth line of the title page reads: to lay down his Commission.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 11".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Huntington, Robert --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116699:1"/>
            <p>SUNDRY REASONS INDUCING Major <hi>Robert HƲNTINGTON</hi> to lay down his Commission.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>HVMBLY</hi> Presented to the Honourable Houses OF PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's ornament</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed in the Yeer. 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:116699:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Some Animadversions on Major</hi> Huntingtons <hi>papers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS Major <hi>Huntington</hi> dealt fast and loose with the Earle of <hi>Manchester</hi> when under him, in hopes of preferment, so now (being out of ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and monies too, in hope of large matters promised) he quarrels with these two eminent Gentlemen, for whom his owne conscience calls him the most unworthyest of men, having alwayes not onely complied with, but till now highly applauded their actions above others. It is well knowne that the first refusing to disband, was concluded by him with others, before either of these knew it. And for the Kings remove by Cornet <hi>Joyce,</hi> those private instructions he gave to some Troopers, can witnesse how far he was ingaged in it, before they knew it, which is of more danger then open speeches at a Councell of War in matters ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to souldiers as souldiers. As for their committing of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, it had been well <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f this Major, and the rest that had such an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon the Agitators, had not hindred that happy agreement which was then so neare, that he complained that they complyed too much with the Kings desires; and had nor their proceedings been obstructed by him, and the persons aforesaid, the King and Parliament had no doubt agreed. It is well knowne to how neare it was brought, and what affronts, threats and mutenies were by his and other Souldiers against I. Gen. <hi>Crumwell,</hi> and Com. Gen. <hi>Ireton</hi> about it. And his owne consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence must needs tell him, how in all debates they pressed to have their actions grounded upon the Authority of Parliament: And to offer his Majesty Chaplaines, wife, children, servants, friends and his Revenue, or what may be to a well grounded peace, upon agreement with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, certainly are no ill principles: nor to make him a glorious Prince up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on settling the Subjects just liberties Neither did he himself dislike, but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved the proposals, &amp; other papers all along And (as himself confesseth) he was a great agent in contriving them and carrying them to the King, &amp; had private conference with the king, who did too much insense his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty against that happy agreement (then so near) with his Parliament, a thing in which these Gentlemen (&amp; others who laboured for peace) much rejoyced in the hopefull expectation thereof. As for pulling the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers cut by the eares, it is not the L. Gen. <hi>Language.</hi> But by his owne papers you may see how forward this Major was then to act in the great busines with the King in which he did many ill offices, in hindring peace then, whereby many a mans blood since spilt, might have been saved, who having spoken (as his conscience knowes) many unbecomming things before his Majesty, now would clear himself, by saying these Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen bad him, as false as the speech he talks on <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the fire side at <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stou;</hi> &amp; other things concerning purging the Houses, &amp; again<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Aldermen. That they should be an Army as long as they live; in which, and other things he plainly discovers his malice. Al which he would excuse with an <hi>I conceive</hi> (at latter end) Now whether this Major be not one of the most wretched Incendiaries in the Kingdome, let any rational man judge.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116699:2"/>
            <head>Sundry Reasons Inducing Major <hi>Robert Huntington</hi> to lay down his Commission.</head>
            <head>Humbly presented to the Honourable Houses of Parliament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving taken up armes in Defence of the authority and Power of King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, under the command of the Lord <hi>Grey of Warke,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Manchester,</hi> during their severall Imployments with the Forces of the Eastern assotiation, and at the model<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of this Army under the present Lord General, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been appointed by the Honorable Houses of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Major to the Now Regiament of Lieutenant Generall <hi>Crumwell,</hi> in each of which imployments having served faithfully and constantly answerable to the trust reposed in me, and having lately quit the said employment, and laid down my Commission, I hold my self tyed both in duty and conscience to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the true reason thereof, which in the generall is briefly this:</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:116699:3"/>
            <p> Because the Principles, Designes, and actions of those Officers, which have a great influence upon the Army, are (as I conceive) very repugnant and destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the Honour and safety of the Parliament and kingdome, from whom they derive their authority, the particulars being a breviate of my sad observations, will appear in the following Narrative.</p>
            <p>First, that upon the Orders of Parliament for Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding this Army, Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and Commissary Generall <hi>Ireton</hi> were sent Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners to <hi>Walden,</hi> to reduce the Army to their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but more especially in Order to the present sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of Forces for the service of <hi>Ireland</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But they contrary to the trust reposed in them, very much hindered that service; not onely by discounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing those that were obedient, and willing, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so by giving incouragement to the unwilling, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient<hi>:</hi> Declaring that there hath lately been much cruelty and injustice in the Parl. proceedings against them (meaning the Army) and Commissary Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Ireton</hi> in further pursuance thereof framed these Papers and Writings then sent from the Army to the Parliament and Kingdome, saying also to the Agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators that it was then lawfull and fit to deny Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding till we had received equall and full satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for our past service, Lieutenant Generall <hi>Crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> further adding, that were in a double capacity as Souldiers, and as Commissioners, and having our pay as Souldiers, we had something else to stand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as Commissioners.</p>
            <p>And when upon the Rendezvouze at <hi>Trypple</hi> Heath the Commissioners of the Parliam. according to their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116699:3"/> Orders acquainted every Regiament with what the Parliament had already done, and would further do in Order to the desire of the Army: the souldiery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before prepared, and notwithstanding any thing that could be said or offered to them by the Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners, they still cryed out for <hi>Justice, Justice.</hi> And for the further effecting of their purposes, advice was given by Lieutenant Generall <hi>Crumwell,</hi> and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missary Generall <hi>Ireton</hi> to remove the Kings person from <hi>Holdenby,</hi> or to secure him there by other guards then those appointed by the Commissioners of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, which was thought most fit to be carried on by the private Souldiery of the Army, and promoted by the Agitators of each Regiament, whose first businesse was to secure the Garrison of <hi>Oxford,</hi> with the Gunnes and Ammunition there, from thence to march to <hi>Holdenby</hi> in prosecution of the former advice which was accordingly acted by Cornet <hi>Ioyce,</hi> who when he had don the businesse sent a Letter to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall then at <hi>Kienton</hi> acquainting his Excellency that the King was on his march towards <hi>New-Market:</hi> The Generall being troubled thereat told Comissary Generall <hi>Ireton</hi> that hee did not like it, Demanding withall who gave those Orders, he replyed that hee gave Orders onely for securing the King there, and not for taking him away from thence, Lieut. Gen. <hi>Crumwnll</hi> comming then from <hi>London,</hi> said, that if this had not been done, the King would have been fetched away by Order of Parliament, or else Col. <hi>Graves</hi> by the advice of the Commissioners would have car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him to <hi>London,</hi> throwing themselves upon the favour of the Parliament for that service: The same
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116699:4"/> day Cornet <hi>Ioyce</hi> being told that the General was dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased with him for bringing the King from <hi>Holden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,</hi> Hee answered that Lieutenant Generall <hi>Crumwell</hi> gave him Order at <hi>London</hi> to doe what he had done both there and at <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Person of the King being now in the power of the Army, the businesse of Lieut. Gen. <hi>Crumwell</hi> was to Court His Majesty, both by Members of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and several Gentlemen formerly in the Kings ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, into a good opinion and beliefe of the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Army, as also into a dis-affection and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of the proceedings of the Par. pretending to show that His Majesties interest would far better suite with the principles of <hi>Independency</hi> then of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and when the King did alleadge (as many times hee did) that the power of Parliament was the power by which we fought, Lieut. Gen. <hi>Crumwell</hi> would reply that we were not onely Souldiers but Commissioners, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mising that the Army would bee for the King, in the settlement of his whole businesse, if the King and His Party would sit still, and not declare against the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but give them leave only to manage the present businesse in hand.</p>
            <p>That when the King was at <hi>New-Market</hi> the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament thought fit to send to His Majesty, humbly desiring that in Order to His safety and their addresses for a speedy settlement, He would be pleased to come to <hi>Richmond:</hi> Contrary hereunto, Resolution was taken by the aforesaid Officers of the Army, if the King could not bee diverted by perswasion, to which His Majesty was very opposite; that then they would stop him by force at <hi>Royston</hi> where his Majesty was to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116699:4"/> lodge the first night, keeping accordingly continuall Guards upon him against any power that should be sent by Order of Parliament to take him from us, and to this purpose Out guards were also kept to prevent his escape from us with the Commissioners, of whom we had speciall orders given to bee carefull, for that they did daily show dislike to the present proceedings of the Army against the Parliament, and that the King was most conversant and private in discourse with them, his Majesty saying, that if any man should hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his going, now his two Houses had desired him, upon his late Message of the 12 of <hi>May,</hi> 1647. it should be done by force, by laying hold of his bridle, which if any were so bold to do, he would indevour to make it his last. But contrary to his Majesties expectation, the next morning when the King and the Officers of the Army were putting this to an issue came the Votes of both Houses to the King, of their compliance with that which the Army formerly desired. After which his Majesty did incline to hearken to the Desires of the Army and not before, whereupon at <hi>Caversham</hi> the King was continually solicited by Messengers from Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and Commissary Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Ireton,</hi> proffering any thing his Majesty should desire: As Revenues, Chaplains, Wife, Children, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of his own, Visitation of Friends, accesse of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, (and by Com. General <hi>Ireton)</hi> that his Negative Voyce should not be medled withall. And that hee had convinced those that reasoned against it in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall councell of the Army, and all this they would doe that his Majesty might the better see into all our actions, and know our principles which lead us to give
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116699:5"/> him all these things out of conscience, for that wee were not a people hating his Majesties person, or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical Government, but that we liked it as the best, and that by <hi>This King.</hi> Saying also that they did hold it a very unreasonable thing for the Parliament to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge him of them. Often promising that if his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty would sit still, and not act against them, they would in the first place restore him to all these, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the settlement of our own just rights and liberties make him the most glorious Prince in Christendome.</p>
            <p>That to this purpose for a settlement they were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king severall Proposals to be offered to the Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of Parli. then sent downe to the Army, which should be as bounds for our party as to the Kings busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And that his Maiesty should have liberty to get as much of those abated as he could, for that many things therein were proposed only to give satisfaction to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who were our friends, promising the King that at the same time the Commissioners of Parliament should see these Proposalls, his Majesty should have a copy of them also, pretending to carry a very equall hand between King and Parliament, in order to the settlement of the kingdome by him; which, besides their own judgements and conscience, they did see a necessity of it, as to the people. Commissary Generall <hi>Ireton</hi> further saying, that what was offered in these proposals, should b<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e so just and reasonable, that if there were but six men in the kingdome, that would fight to make them good, he would make the seventh against any power that should oppose them.</p>
            <p>The Head-quarters being removed from <hi>Redding</hi> to <hi>Bedford,</hi> His Majesty to <hi>Wooburne,</hi> the Proposals
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116699:5"/> were given to me by Comis. Gen. <hi>Ireton</hi> to present to the King, which His Majesty having read, told me that he would never Treate with the Army nor the Parliament, upon these Proposals as hee was then minded, but the next day His Majesty understanding that a Force was put upon His Houses of Parliament by a tumult, sent for mee, and said unto me, goe a long with Sir <hi>John Barkeley</hi> to your Generall, and Lieut. Gen. and tell them, that, to avoid a new war I will now Treate with them upon their Proposalls, or any thing else, in order to a Peace, onely let me be saved in Honour, and Conscience, Sir <hi>John Barkley</hi> falling sicke by the way, I delivered this Message to the Lieut. Generall, and to Commis. Gen. <hi>Ireton,</hi> who advised mee not to acquaint the Generall with it till 10 or 12 Officers of the Army were met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the Generalls Quarters, and then they would bethinke themselves of some persons to be sent to the King about it, and accordingly Com. Gen. <hi>Ireton,</hi> Col. <hi>Rainsborough,</hi> Col. <hi>Hammond</hi> and Col. <hi>Rich</hi> attended the King at <hi>Wooburne</hi> for three houres toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, debating the whole businesse with the King up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Proposals, upon which Debates, many of the most materiall things the King dis-liked were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards strucke out, and many other things much abat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by promises: whereupon his Majesty was satisfied, within a day or two after this, his Majesty removed to <hi>Stoke,</hi> and there calling for me, told me, He feared an Ingagement between the City and the Army, saying he had not time to write any thing under His hand, but would send it to the Generall after mee, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding to tell Com. Gen <hi>Ireton</hi> with whom he had formerly Treated upon the Proposals, that He would
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116699:6"/> wholly throw himselfe upon us, and trust us with the settlement of the Kingdome as we had promised; say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if wee proved honest men, we should without question make the Kingdom happy, and save much shedding of blood, this Message from His Majesty I delivered to Com. Gen. <hi>Ireton</hi> in <hi>Colebrooke,</hi> who seemed to receive it with joy, saying that we should be the veriest knaves that ever lived, if in every thing wee made not good whatever wee had promised, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the King by His not Declaring against us, had given us great advantage against our adversaries.</p>
            <p>After our marching through <hi>London</hi> with the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, His Majesty being at <hi>Hampton Court</hi> Lieut. Gen. <hi>Crumwell</hi> and Com. Gen. <hi>Ireton</hi> sent the King word severall times, That the Reason why they made no more hast in his busines; was, because that that Party which did then sit in the House while <hi>Pelham</hi> was spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, did much obstruct the busines, so that they could not carry it on at present Lieut. Gen. often saying that <hi>Really, they should bee pulled out by cares,</hi> and to that purpose caused a Regiment of Horse to Randezvouze at <hi>Hide-Parke</hi> to have put that in execution as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe exprest, had it not beene carried by Vote in the House that day as he desired.</p>
            <p>The day before the Parliament Voted once more the sending up of the Propositions of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes to the King, by the Commissioners of each Kingdom at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> Commis. Gen. <hi>Ireton</hi> bad me tell the King that such a thing was to be done to morrow in the House, but His Majesty need not be troubled at it: For that they intended it to no other end, but to make good some promises of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116699:6"/> which the Nation of <hi>Scotland</hi> expected the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of, &amp; that it was not expected or desired his Majesty should either signe or treat upon them, for which there should be no advantage taken against the King; upon the delivery of which message, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty replyed, He knew not what answer to give to please all, without a Treaty.</p>
            <p>Next day after this Vote passed, Lieu. Generall as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked me hereupon, if the King did not wonder at these Votes<hi>:</hi> I told him no: for that Com. Gen. <hi>Ireton</hi> had sent such a message by me the day before the Vote passed, to signifie the reason of it; the Liev. Generall replyed, that really it was the truth, and that we, (speaking of the Parliament) intended nothing else, but to satisfie the Scot, which otherwise might bee troublesome. And the Liev. Generall, and Com. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, enquiring after his Majesty answer'd to the Proposition, and what it would be, it was shewed them both privately in a Garden-house at Putney, and in some part amended to their own minds. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this, the King doubting what answer to give, sent me to Liev. Generall <hi>Crumwell</hi> as unsatisfied with the proceedings of the Army, hearing they intended not to make good what they had promised, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther because his Majesty understood that Liev. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Crumwell,</hi> Com. Generall <hi>Ireton</hi> agreed with the rest of the House in some late Votes that opposed the Proposalls of the Army<hi>:</hi> They readily replied, that they would not have his Majesty mistrust them, for that since the House would goe so high, they one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concurred with them, that their unreasonablenesse might the better appeare to the Kingdome; and Liev.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116699:7"/> Generall bad me further assure the King, That if the Army remained an Army, his Majesty should trust the Proposalls, with what was promised to be the worst of his condition, which should bee made for him. And then striking his hand on his heart in his chamber at Putney, bad me tell the King, he might rest confident and assured of it; and many times the same message hath been sent to the King from them both, but with this addition from Com. Gen. <hi>Ireton,</hi> That they would purge, and purge, &amp; purge, and never leave purging the Houses, till they had made them of such a temper as should doe his Majesties businesse, and rather then they would fal short of what was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised, he would joyne with French, Spaniard, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, or any that would joyne with him to force them to it, upon the delivery of which message, the King made answer, That if they doe, they would do more then he durst doe.</p>
            <p>After this, the delay of the settlement of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, was excused upon the commotions of Col. <hi>Martin,</hi> and Col. <hi>Rainsborough,</hi> with their adherents, the Liev. Generall saying, That speedy course must be taken for outing of them in the House and Army, because they were now putting the Army into a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teny, by having hands in publishing severall Printed papers, calling themselves the Agents of five, and the agreement of the people, although some men had incouragement from Liev. Generall <hi>Crummell</hi> for the prosecution of those papers; and he being further prest to shew himselfe in it, desired to be excused at present, for that he might shew himself better for their advantage hereafter, though in the company of those
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116699:7"/> men which were of different judgements, he would often say, that these people were a giddy headed par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that there was no trust or truth in them. And to that purpose wrote a letter to Col. <hi>Whaley</hi> that day the King went from <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, intimating doubtfully that his Majesties person was in danger by them. And that hee should keep Out-guards to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them, which was presently shewed the King by Col. <hi>Whaley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That about six dayes after it was fully knowne by the Parliament and Army, that the King was in the Isle of <hi>Wight,</hi> Commissary Generall <hi>Ireton</hi> standing by the fire side at his Quarters at <hi>Kingston,</hi> and some speaking of an agreement likely to be made betweene the King and Parliament, now the person of the king was out of the power of the Army; Com. Generall <hi>Ireton</hi> replyed with a discontented countenance, That he hoped it would be such a peace as we might with a good conscience fight against them both.</p>
            <p>Thus they who at the first taking the King from <hi>Holdenby</hi> into the power of the Army, cryed downe Presbyterian government, the proceedings of this present Parliament, and their perpetuity, and instead thereof, held forth an earnest inclination to a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Episcopacy, with a new election of Members to sit in Parliament for a speedy settlement of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And afterwards when the eleven Members had left the House, and the marching through <hi>London</hi> with the Army, the seven Lords impeached, the four Aldermen of <hi>London</hi> committed to the Tower, and other Citizens committed also; then againe they cryed up Presbyterian government, the perpetuity of this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116699:8"/> present Parliament: Liev. Gen. <hi>Crumwell</hi> further plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing himselfe with the great summes of money which were in arreare from each County to the Army, and the taxe of 60000 li. <hi>per</hi> moneth for our maintenance, <hi>Now</hi> (saith he) <hi>we may be for ought</hi> I <hi>know, an Army as long as we live.</hi> And since the sending forth the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Parliament for the calling of the Members to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, Liev. Generall <hi>Crumwel</hi> perceiving the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses will not answer his expectation, he is now againe uttering words perswading the hearers to a prejudice against the proceedings of Parliament; again crying downe Presbyterian government, setting up a single interest, which he calls an honest Interest, and that we have done ill in forsaking of it.—To this purpose it was lately thought fit to put the Army upon the choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing new Agitators, and to draw forth of the Houses of Parliament 60 or 70 of the Members thereof, much agreeing with his words hee spake formerly at his chamber in <hi>Kingston,</hi> saying, What a sway <hi>Stappleton,</hi> &amp; <hi>Hollis</hi> had heretofore in the Kingdome, and he knew nothing to the contrary, but that he was as well able to governe the Kingdome as either of them<hi>:</hi> so that in all his discourse nothing more appeareth then his seeking after the government of King, Parliament, City and Kingdome; for the effecting whereof, hee thought it necessary, and delivered it as his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that a considerable party of the chiefe Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> and some of every County be clapt up in Castles and Garrisons for the quiet and submissive carriage of every place to which they belong. Further saying, that from the raising of the late tumult in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> there should be an occasion taken to hang the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116699:8"/> Recorder and Aldermen of <hi>London</hi> then in the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that the City might see the more they did stir in opposition, the more they should suffer: Adding that the City must first be made an example. And since that Lieut. Gen. <hi>Crúmwell</hi> was sent downe from the Parliament: for the reducing of the Army to their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, he hath most frequently in publique and private delivered these insuing heads as his principles from whence all the aforegoing particulars have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued being fully confirmed (as I humbly conceive) by his practise in the Transactions of his last years bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse: as,</p>
            <p n="1">1 That every single man is judge of Just and Right as to the good or ill of a Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That the Interest of honest men is the Interest of the Kingdom, and that those only are deemed honest men by him, that are conformable to his judgement and practise, as may appeare in many particulars, to instance but in one: In the choice of Col. <hi>Rainsbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough</hi> to be Vice-Admirall, Lieut. Gen. <hi>Crumwell</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked how hee could trust a man whose interest was so directly opposite, and what he had professed, and one whom he had lately aimed to remove fromal places of trust, he answered, that he had now received particular assurance from Col. <hi>Rainsborough</hi> (as great as could be given by man) that he would be conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the judgement and direction of himselfe and Com. G. <hi>Ireton</hi> for the managing the whole businesse at Sea.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That it is lawfull to passe through any formes of government for the accomplishing his ends, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore either to purge the Houses, and support the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116699:9"/> party by force everlastingly, or to put a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to them by force, is very lawful and sutable to the interest of honest men.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That it is lawfull to play the knave with a knave.</p>
            <p>These Gent. aforesaid (in the Army) thus principled, &amp; as by many other circumstances might appear acting accordingly give too much cause to beleeve that the successe which may be obtained by the Army, except timely prevented by the wisdome of the Parl. will be made use of to the destroying of all their power for which wee first ingaged, and having for above these 12 monthes past sadly and with much reluctance ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served these severall passages aforesaid yet with some hopes that there might be a returning to the obedience of the Parliament, and contrary thereunto knowing that Resolutions were taken up that in case the power of Parliament cannot be gained to countenance their Designe, then to proceed without it.</p>
            <p>I therefore chose to quit my selfe of my command wherein I have served the Parliament for these five yeares last past, and put my selfe upon the greatest hazzards, by discoverning these truthes, rather then by hopes of gaine, with a troubled mind, continue an Abetter or Assistant of such as give affronts to the Parliament and Kingdome, by abusing the Power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to carry on their particular designes. Against whom in the middest of danger, I shal avowe the truth of this narative: And my selfe to be a constant, faithfull, and obedient Servant to the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>August</hi> 2. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Robert Huntington.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>